Leland Boyd Henry Papers
Leland Boyd Henry Papers
1835-1968
Henry, Leland Boyd, 1895-1968.
8.7 linear ft.
Papers of the American clergyman, social activist. Henry was a Methodist Episcopal, later, Protestant Episcopal minister. Collection includes sermons (1925-1967); speeches; and scrapbooks (1914-1965).
149047
Biographical History
Leland Boyd Henry (1895-1968) was an American clergyman and social activist. Born June 3, 1895 in Buffalo, New York, the son of Charles Edward and Eva Boyd Henry. he graduated from Buffalo Central High School in 1914. He then entered Syracuse University where he participated in a variety of activities and was successively reporter, associate editor, managing editor and editor of the campus newspaper, the Daily Orange.
In 1918 Dr. Henry graduated from Syracuse, married Ruth Van Arsdale, a classmate, and entered the United States Army as a sergeant with the 39th Infantry in France. There he served on the Marne and in the Argonne and was awarded the Purple Heart.
Upon release from military service he entered Drew Theological Seminary, from which he received the Bachelor of Divinity degree in 1922, and spent the following year in further study at Cambridge University. When he returned to the United States he served as a minister at Asbury Methodist Episcopal Church in Buffalo, the church at Newfane and the Corn Hill Methodist Episcopal Church of Rochester, all in New York State.
In 1930 Dr. and Mrs. Henry became members of the Protestant Episcopal Church and Dr. Henry sought admission to its priesthood. In September he began work as an educational assistant at St. Paul's Church in Rochester and was ordained to the priesthood in 1931. In 1932 he became rector of St. Luke's Parish in Brockport, New York, and in 1937 was called to serve as assistant to the rector at St. George's Church in New York City, a position he held until 1942 when he entered the military chaplaincy. He spent the early part of the war teaching in chaplains' schools but during its later stages served as chaplain on the hospital ship St. Mihiel in the Atlantic and Pacific.
Upon his return to New York in 1946 Dr. Henry was appointed executive secretary of the Social Service Commission of the Diocese of New York, which in the same year was renamed the Christian Social Relations Commission. The National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church appointed him as its observer at the United Nations beginning in 1949. Dr. Henry was a logical choice for this post because of his great concern for problems of world order and his active involvement in seeking creative solutions.
In 1955 Dr. Henry was appointed to the Human Rights Commission of New York City. During his tenure he was actively involved in attempts to improve housing for low-income families and his efforts in this direction brought him an honorary Doctor of Divinity degree from Lincoln University.
Dr. Henry's wife, Ruth, died in 1947 and in 1950 he married his second wife, Beatrice M. Hetzler. A year later he became rector of St. Mary's Church in Scarborough, New York, where he served until his retirement in 1965. He continued with the diocesan commission on a part-time basis until 1957 when he resigned as executive director.
In June 1968 Dr. Henry was awarded an honorary Doctor of Sacred Theology degree by Syracuse University. He died three months later on August 31, 1968.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leland Boyd Henry Papers consist of writings, memorabilia and printed material.
Writings include sermons, speeches and a study guide. Sermons are dated according to Dr. Henry's own system, by the Sundays of the church year beginning with the Advent season, with the place of delivery noted in each instance. A series of sermons delivered on holidays not included in the church follows. A folder of sermon research material also is included. In almost every instance the sermons are original typescripts revised.
Speeches, mostly revised transcripts, all originate in the period when Dr. Henry was executive director of the Commission on Christian Social Relations of the Episcopal Diocese of New York.
The study guide, 1946, was prepared by Dr. Henry for use by church groups in studying the Christian basis for concern about problems of world order. It is a mimeographed copy.
The speeches and the study guide especially reflect Dr. Henry's concern for the implications of the Christian faith for social problems. Although the sermons deal with all the major themes and concepts of the Christian faith, they also reflect his particular social concern.
Memorabilia includes biographical materials, confirmation instruction, orders of worship and miscellaneous items. The biographical materials consist of ten scrapbooks which contain photographs, newspaper clippings, programs, playbills, invitations and a few letters. The confirmation materials are outlines used by Dr. Henry to instruct confirmation classes of young people and adults. The orders of worship were used by Dr. Henry in conducting church services and are arranged chronologically. The miscellaneous materials contain bulletins, programs of Christian Social Relations conferences and a copy of the first newsletter of the Commission on Christian Social Relations.
Printed material consists of books and pamphlets from Dr. Henry's library. The collection consists of copies of the Bible, the Book of Common Prayer, published sermons, reports of church conferences and educational materials. Speeches are arranged alphabetically by title.
Arrangement of the Collection
Sermons are arranged in church calendar order and within that chronologically by year. Where a sermon was delivered more than once, it will be found under the Sunday on which it was first delivered. A series of sermons delivered on holidays not included in the church year are arranged chronologically by the date of the holiday and within that order by the dates on which they were first preached. A miscellaneous series of sermons is arranged alphabetically by title. Memorabilia is subdivided by type and within that arranged chronologically. Printed material is subdivided by type and arranged alphabetically by author or title within that.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Henry, Leland Boyd, 1895-1968 -- Archives.; Episcopal Church, Clergy.; Methodist Episcopal Church, Clergy.; Church and the world.; Clergy -- United States.; Episcopalians -- United States.; Sermons, American.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.; Speeches (documents); Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Leland Boyd Henry, 1969.
Inventory
- Writings
  - Sermons
    - First Sunday in Advent, 1942-1964; 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Second Sunday in Advent, 1947-1963; 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Third Sunday in Advent, 1932-1963; 14 folders (Box 1)
    - Fourth Sunday in Advent, 1934-1964; 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Christmas Eve, 1933-1963; 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Christmas, 1925-1964; 12 folders (Box 1)
    - Holy Innocents Day, 1952 (Box 1)
    - First Sunday after Christmas, 1934-1961; 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Watch Night, 1937-1945; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Second Sunday after Christmas, 1953-1963; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Epiphany, 1957-1965 (Box 2)
    - First Sunday after Epiphany, 1950-1964; 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Second Sunday after Epiphany, 1935-1965; 14 folders (Box 2)
    - Third Sunday after Epiphany, 1948-1965; 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Fourth Sunday after Epiphany, 1952-1965; 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Fifth Sunday after Epiphany, 1954-1965; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Sixth Sunday after Epiphany, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Septuagesima Sunday, 1947-1967; 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Sexagesima Sunday, 1948-1965; 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Quinquagesima Sunday, 1948-1965; 11 folders (Box 3)
    - Lent, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Ash Wednesday, 1936-1965; 8 folders (Box 3)
    - First Sunday in Lent, 1948-1965; 14 folders (Box 3)
    - Second Sunday in Lent, 1946-1965; 14 folders (Box 3)
    - Third Sunday in Lent, 1954-1964; 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Fourth Sunday in Lent, 1962-1965; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Passion Sunday, 1948-1965; 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Palm Sunday, 1932-1965; 16 folders (Box 4)
    - Wednesday before Easter, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Maundy Thursday, 1939-1965; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Good Friday, 1938-1965; 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Easter Sunday, 1926-1965; 19 folders (Box 4)
    - Lent, 1953 (Box 4)
    - First Sunday after Easter, 1933-1966; 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Second Sunday after Easter, 1940-1965; 10 folders (Box 5)
    - Third Sunday after Easter, 1934-1965; 13 folders (Box 5)
    - Fourth Sunday after Easter, 1949-1967; 11 folders (Box 5)
    - Fifth Sunday after Easter, 1933-1964; 15 folders (Box 5)
    - Ascension Day, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Sunday after Ascension, 1950-1965; 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Whitsunday, 1932-1967; 14 folders (Box 5)
    - Trinity Sunday, 1952-1964; 8 folders (Box 6)
    - First Sunday after Trinity, 1935-1967; 12 folders (Box 6)
    - Second Sunday after Trinity, 1954-1965; 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Third Sunday after Trinity, 1932-1962; 11 folders (Box 6)
    - Fourth Sunday after Trinity, 1941-1966; 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Fifth Sunday after Trinity, 1941-1965; 12 folders (Box 6)
    - Sixth Sunday after Trinity, 1938-1964; 11 folders (Box 6)
    - Seventh Sunday after Trinity, 1941-1961; 8 folders (Box 7)
    - Eighth Sunday after Trinity, 1932-1963; 9 folders (Box 7)
    - Ninth Sunday after Trinity, 1940-1961; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Eleventh Sunday after Trinity, 1941-1960; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Twelfth Sunday after Trinity, 1940-1965; 8 folders (Box 7)
    - Thirteenth Sunday after Trinity, 1940-1965; 11-folders (Box 7)
    - Fourteenth Sunday after Trinity, 1940-1964; 11 folders (Box 7)
    - Fifteenth Sunday after Trinity, 1941-1965; 13 folders (Box 7)
    - Sixteenth Sunday after Trinity, 1953-1963; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Seventeenth Sunday after Trinity, 1954-1962; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Eighteenth Sunday after Trinity, 1953-1963; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Nineteenth Sunday after Trinity, 1952-1964; 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Twentieth Sunday after Trinity, 1941-1963; 8 folders (Box 8)
    - Twenty-first Sunday after Trinity, 1953-1964; 10 folders (Box 8)
    - Twenty-second Sunday after Trinity, 1951-1964; 10 folders (Box 8)
    - Twenty-third Sunday after Trinity, 1951-1964; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Twenty-fourth Sunday after Trinity, 1951-1962; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - All Saints Day, 1940-1964; 6 folders (Box 9)
    - Twenty-fifth Sunday after Trinity, 1951-1956; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Twenty-sixth Sunday after Trinity, 1936-1964; 7 folders (Box 9)
    - Memorial Day, 1943-1961; 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Independence Day, 1959 (Box 9)
    - Labor Day, 1953 (Box 9)
    - Thanksgiving Day, 1938-1963; 8 folders (Box 9)
    - Quiet Day for Women, 1954-1961; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "The Church and War", undated (Box 9)
      - "The Fact and Schism and the Search for Unity", 1961 (Box 9)
      - "The Race Problem Today", 1961 (Box 9)
      - "The Survival Value of Christianity", 1949 (Box 9)
      - "The Teachings of the Bible on War", 1951-1952 (Box 9)
      - Untitled (On American Foreign Policy) (Box 9)
      - Research material (Box 9)
  - Speeches
    - "Christian Social Relations", 1951-1953 (Box 9)
    - "Christian Social Relations in the Parish", 1949 (Box 9)
    - "The Church and Society", 1951 (Box 9)
    - "Church Social Services Today", 1952 (Box 9)
    - "The Churches and War", 1950 (Box 9)
    - "The Moral Dilemma of the U.N.", undated (Box 9)
    - "Released Time", 1949 (Box 9)
    - "The Search for Peace", 1951 (Box 9)
    - "United States Responsibility in the World Community", 1953 (Box 9)
  - Study Guide
    - Christian Principles of World Order, 1946 (Box 9)
- Memorabilia
  - Biographical material
    - Scrapbooks
      - 1914-1918, 1921 (Package 1)
      - 1922-1923 (Package 2)
      - 1929-1933, 1946-1947 (Package 3)
      - 1948 (Package 4)
      - 1948-1949 (Package 5)
      - 1950 (Package 6)
      - 1951 (Package 7)
      - 1952-1955 (Package 8)
      - 1955-1957 (Package 9)
      - 1958, 1963-1965 (Package 10)
  - Confirmation materials (Box 9)
  - Orders of worship, 1955-1965 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 28 items (Box 9)
- Printed material
  - Books
    - Bible. O.T. Apocrypha. Rev. version. N.Y., Thomas Nelson [ 1895] Signed. (Vol. 1) (Box 10)
    - Bible. N.T. English. N.Y., New York Bible Society, undated (Byrd Antarctic Expedition) Presentation copy. (Vol. 2) (Box 10)
    - Bible. N.T. Greek. N.Y., Macmillan, 1921. Bound with Hickie, W.J. (Box 10)
    - Greek-English lexicon to the New Testament. N.Y., Macmillan, 1921 (Vol. 3) (Box 10)
    - Bible. N.T. Latin. England, Berolini, 1925. (Vol. 4) (Box 10)
    - The Book of Common Prayer. (Pages missing, including title page) Bound with Psalms, in metre. N.Y., Protestant Episcopal Church, 1835. (Vol. 5) (Box 10)
    - The Book of Common Prayer. Cambridge University Press, undated (Vol. 6) (Box 10)
    - The book of offices; services for certain occasions not provided for in the Book of Common Prayer. 2d. ed. N.Y., Church Pension Fund, 1949. (Vol. 7) (Box 10)
    - The calendar and the collects, epistles, and gospels for the lesser feasts and for special occasions. N.Y., Church Pension Fund, 1963. Letter from the Rt. Rev. Horace W.B. Donegan taped in front. (Vol. 8) (Box 10)
    - Cavanah, Frances and Lloyd E. Smith, comp. I am an American; what we all are fighting for. Racine, Wisc., Whitman [ c. 1940, 1942] (Vol. 9) (Box 10)
    - The Church of Scotland. Reports to the General Assembly, 1968. England, William Blackwood [ 1968?] (Vol. 10) (Box 10)
    - Dearmer, Percy, R. Vaughn Williams, and Martin Shaw. The Oxford book of carols. London, Oxford University Press, 1928. (Vol. 11) (Box 10)
    - Dodd, C.H. Three sermons. London, SCM Press, 1954. Inscribed and signed by Dick Beebe. (Box 10)
    - The first and second prayer-books of King Edward the Sixth. London, J.M. Dent [ 1927] (Everyman's Library, no. 448) (Vol. 12) (Box 10)
    - Hymns ancient and modern. Rev. London, William Clowes, 1950. Autographed. (Vol. 13) (Box 10)
    - Lambeth Conference 1948. London, S.P.C.K., 1948 (Vol. 14) (Box 10)
    - Lambeth Conference 1958. [London] S.P.C.K. and Seabury Press, 1958. (Vol. 15) (Box 10)
    - Prayer book studies. N.Y., Church Pension Fund.
      - I Baptism and confirmation. (Box 10)
      - II The liturgical lectionary., 1950 (Box 10)
      - III The Order for the ministration to the sick., 1951 (Box 10)
      - IV The Eucharistic liturgy., 1953 (Box 10)
      - VI Morning and evening prayer. (Box 10)
      - VII The penitential office., 1957 (Box 10)
      - XVII The liturgy of the Lord's Supper., 1966 (Box 10)
    - Prayers new and old. Cincinnati, Forward Movement Commission. Annotated. (Vol. 16), c. 1937 (Box 10)
    - Prayers for private devotion in war-time. Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Printing Office. Autographed by Willard L. Sperry. (Vol. 17), undated (Box 10)
    - Robertson, Frederick W. Sermons on religion and life. London, J.M. Dent (Everyman's Library, no. 37) Signed. (Vol. 18), 1917 (Box 10)
    - The Scottish Book of Common Prayer. Edinburgh, Cambridge University Press (Vol. 19), 1929 (Box 10)
    - Thirkfield, Wilbur Patterson. Service and prayers for church and home. N.Y., Methodist Book Concern (Vol. 20), c. 1918, 1920 (Box 11)
  - Pamphlets
    - The liturgy of the Lord's Supper... (mimeographed) (Box 11)
    - The new liturgy; the liturgy of the Lord's supper,... N.Y. Morehouse-Barlow., 1966 (Box 11)
    - Wolf, Frederick and Barbara. Reading pamphlets 1-10. Greenwich, Conn., Seabury Press., c. 1960 (Box 11)